Guide to the Arthur H. Landis Oral History Collection ALBA.AUDIO.066
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Arthur H. Landis Oral History Collection
1963-1965
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Landis, Arthur H., 1917-1986
ALBA.AUDIO.066
6 Linear Feet
Arthur H. Landis (1917-1986) went to Spain in 1937 as a volunteer with the 15th International Brigade and fought with the MacKenzie-Papineau Battalion. In 1967, Landis wrote The Abraham Lincoln Brigade, a general history of American volunteers in the Spanish Civil War, and later published Spain! The Unfinished Revolution, about the political complexities of the war. The Landis collection of audiotapes consists primarily of interviews with American Spanish Civil War veterans conducted in the 1960s as part of his research for The Abraham Lincoln Brigade. A few miscellaneous tapes recorded for other purposes are also included.
(71 1/4" reel-to-reel tapes and 89 audiocassettes)
Provenance
The Arthur H. Landis Oral History Collection was donated to the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives by Arthur H. Landis in the early 1980s. The collection came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University. The audiotapes in the Arthur H. Landis Collection were separated from the Arthur H. Landis Papers at the time of processing.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Historical/Biographical Note
Arthur H. Landis (1917-1986) went to Spain in 1937 to join the 15th International Brigade; he served with the MacKenzie-Papineau Battalion, as an American volunteer in what became a predominantly Canadian unit. In 1967, Landis wrote The Abraham Lincoln Brigade, a general history of American volunteers in the Spanish Civil War, and later published Spain! The Unfinished Revolution, about the political complexities of the war.
The Arthur H. Landis Oral History Collection is comprised primarily of approximately 100 hours of audio-taped recordings of American veterans of the Spanish Civil War. The original 1/4" tapes were created between 1963 and 1965 as part of the research for Landis's The Abraham Lincoln Brigade. Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB) associates around the country, alone and in small groups, recorded their memories of battles and day-to-day activities in which they had participated.
The idea of audio-taping veterans first occurred to Landis in April of 1963, and by August 1964 the project was gathering steam. On August 10th Landis sent a letter to VALB associate Donald Thayer in San Francisco detailing the information that he was seeking from SCW veterans. Thayer excerpted Landis's letter in a general mailing to VALB members, requesting that they make their own audiotapes, in which they were to supply detailed information about their battalions, units, firepower, orders received, positions occupied, nature of attacks, terrain conditions, day-to-day positions, casualties and prisoners, wins and losses, "human-interest vignettes," promotions or substitutions, and related information. Landis emphasized that he still badly needed information on Aragon, Teruel, the Retreats, and the Ebro. A decade after the research was completed, Landis recalled that the tapes contained the "detailed examination of American brigade and battalion involvement in a particular battle or series of battles in a particular campaign, and/or the structure, personnel and participation in action of a unit such as transport, artillery, the American Medical Bureau, etc." At least 20 of the tapings were not personally attended by Landis, but were produced according to his explicit instructions. Veterans Steve Nelson and Donald Thayer conducted a handful of the interviews. After Landis completed a draft of the book, veterans in VALB's New York office met and recorded their suggestions for changes (tapes ALBA A 66-2 and ALBA A 66-36).
Landis's research project stimulated intense interest among VALB members. Donald Thayer reported that when he played a tape made for Landis by a veteran for a group of VALB members, it stirred in the vets "all of the memories of the Brigade years."
Responding to a comment in 1977 by veteran Randall "Pete" Smith that Landis had downplayed the involvement of a fellow SCW veteran in his book, Landis recounted in a detailed letter the way in which veterans had been notified about the project, charging the New York VALB office with neglecting to invite the participation of a number of vets.
In the late sixties, Landis tried to interest the VALB leadership in funding a project to preserve the audiotapes, and later proposed a project that went beyond preservation. He explained his reasons for wanting to embark on this project in a 1974 letter to Brandeis University Special Collections Librarian Victor Berch, arguing that "new tapes [should] be made--and quickly, before the rest of us die off." Landis further proposed to "edit and re-tape" the tapes he had of vets who had already died. This project does not appear to have been carried out. But in the 1980s the reel-to-reel tapes were copied to audiocassettes.
For further biographical information on Arthur Landis, and for more information on the audiotape project see, Arthur H. Landis Papers, ALBA #66.
Scope and Content Note
For the audiotape project Landis provided veterans with a demo tape (ALBA A 66-038) that "gave the outline structure of the book and a detailed explanation of his desire to give adequate attention to all phases of the war which Americans participated in, from ambulance drivers to the commando zealots." Further, Landis stressed: "material for taping [should] be put in chronological order to avoid a time-consuming play-back," that veterans "make notes before making the tape," and "tape at a speed of 3-1/4." Members were told that they could use their own tape recorders, or that VALB would loan out both a recorder and tapes.
The tapes were not professionally recorded, nor were the sessions conducted as conventional oral histories. Consequently, the sound quality varies from tape to tape, and veterans at times do not identify themselves or provide many autobiographical details. The focus is on their day-by-day participation in the Spanuish Civil War.
Series I: Reel-to-Reel Tapes. Book Project, 1963-1965, contains individual and group interviews conducted in the course of research for Arthur Landis's book, The Abraham Lincoln Brigade, and one demo tape produced by Landis.
Series II: Miscellaneous Reel-to-Reel Tapes, 1945-1970, consists mostly of interviews with Spanish Civil War veterans, some commenting on Landis's published work, and music tapes, several of which feature singer (and veteran) Bart Van der Schelling singing songs of the Spanish Civil War. Van der Schelling is pictured with Paul Robeson and Arthur Landis, among others, in a photograph in the Arthur H. Landis Photo Collection.
The availability of CD reference copies and audiocassettes copies in indicated in the entries for individual items. Reel-to-reel tapes labeled "not transferable" in the descriptions were damaged or posed other serious problems that prevented transferring them to CD.
Arrangement
Each tape has been assigned a unique item number (i.e., ALBA A 48-11), and the collection is arranged in item number order. In general, the tapes are arranged alphabetically by the first name mentioned in the caption.
Entries in the reel-to-reel item lists indicate whether there is a CD reference copy and/or audiocassette copies. The reference CDs are numbered to correspond with the reel-to-reel numbers (followed by an "R") and are stored separately. Cassette copies are numbered ALBA A 66-72 through ALBA A 66-160 and are arranged numerically and stored separately.
The files are organized in 2 series:
Missing Title
I, Reel-to-Reel Tapes, Book Project, 1963-1965.
II, Miscellaneous Reel-to-Reel Tapes, 1945-1970.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
ALBA collections at the Tamiment Library.
Arthur H. Landis Papers (ALBA 66)
Arthur H. Landis Photograph Collection (ALBA Photo 66)
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Access copies for sound recordings may be available by appointment for reading room listening only. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information, to request digitization of materials, and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Women.; Murcia (Spain); Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Personal narratives.; Albacete (Spain); Valencia (Spain); Audiocassettes.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Hospitals.; Madrid (Spain); Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Schulman, Rebecca (Durem); Secundy, Louis; Quinones, Gabriel Jack; Fishman, Mosess (Moe), 1916-2007; Schelling, Bart van der, 1892-1970; Pappas, Nick; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Munday, Arthur; Nelson, Steve, 1903-1993; Wolff, Milton.; Geiser, Carl; Fisher, Harry, 1911-2003; Nusser, Charles; Goff, Irving; Goddard, Howard, 1911-1997; Chaikin, George, 1908-1992; Warren, Alvin; Brown, Archie, 1911-1990.; Smith, Randall, 1917-1989; Goldstein, Benjamin, 1910-1985; Cane, Lawrence, 1912-1976; Smith, Harold; Osheroff, Abe; Zlotnick, Louis; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade. Historical Commission; Harriman, Manny; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade. Archives; Wellman, Wilbur Ed; Brandt, Joseph, 1909-1997; Wheeler, William Gilmore; Parker, Max, 1912-1983.; Klein, Herman (Gabby); Thayer, Donald; Houlihan, Sara; Groden, Daniel Samuel; Haber, Cohn; Sennett, William, 1914-; Tivin, Isidore; Van Clute, Walton.; Shaker, Kenneth R.; Stuart, Yale; Bevensee, Court; Blair, John; Thompson, Robert George, 1915-1966; MacLeod, Donald; Davidow, Ruth; Taft, Anne, 1912-1990; Landis, Arthur H., 1917-1986; Gittelson, Lester; Foucek, George; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Brigada Internacional, XV; Berch, Victor A.; Klonsky, Robert; Barsky, Edward K., 1895-1975; Hutchins, Evelyn, 1910-1982; Kusman, Felix, 1909-1983; Love, Vaughn; Levine, Sidney R.; McNeil, Allan; Eider, Louis; Hyman, Frank Chesler; Colow, Maury; Keir, Duncan, Jr.; Kaufman, Rubin; Keller, Ruth; Keller, Fred Paul
- Series I: Reel-to-Reel Tapes, 1962-1965.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Access copies for some recordings are available by appointment for reading room listening only. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives with collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
  - Barsky, Edward; Duncan Keir, Jr. [audiocassettes 66-72, 66-73, 66-74] (CD reference copy available), undated (Box 1, Item 66- 1)
  - Bevensee, Court; and Moe Fishman. Second and Last Session on Brunete and Bevensee's comments on the draft of Landis' book. [audiocassette 66-75] (CD reference copy available), undated (Box 1, Item 66- 2)
  - Blair, John; and [Cohn Haber?] Discussing the structure of the MacKenzie-Papineau Battalion and joining the 15th Brigade outside of Quinto. [audiocassettes 66-76, 66-77, 66-78, 66-79] (CD reference copy available), undated (Box 1, Item 66- 3)
  - Brandt, Joe. [audiocassettes 66-80, 66-81, 66-82, 66-83] [Not transferable], undated (Box 1, Item 66- 4)
  - Brown, Archie; George Foucek; Sidney Levine; and Donald Thayer. On re-crossing of the Ebro. [audiocassette 66-84] (CD reference copy available), Oct 31, 1964 (Box 1, Item 66- 5)
  - Brown, Archie; George Foucek; Sidney Levine; and Donald Thayer. Continuing the discussion of Gandesa, while Foucek describes activities leading up to Hill 666. [audiocassette 66-85] (CD reference copy available), undated (Box 1, Item 66- 6)
  - Cane, Lawrence (Larry); and Carl Geiser. [audiocassette 66-86] (CD reference copy available), undated (Box 1, Item 66- 7)
  - Cane, Lawrence (Larry); and Milton Wolff. [audiocassette 66-87] (CD reference copy available), undated (Box 1, Item 66- 8)
  - Chaiken, George; and Felix Kusman. Kusman discusses the action at Quinto and Belchite, and what the company did on the first, second and third day at Quinto. [audiocassette 66-88] (CD reference copy available), undated (Box 1, Item 66- 9)
  - Chesler, Frank; and Max Robert Klonsky. Klonsky describes late 1936 when he agreed to go to Spain and how he went to the Army & Navy store in lower Manhattan to get equipment. [audiocassettes 66-91, 66-92] [Not transferable], undated (Box 1, Item 66- 10)
  - Chesler, Frank; and Robert Thompson. Discussing Fuentes del Ebro on the Aragon Front where [?] commanded the MacKenzie-Papineau Canadian Battalion. [audiocassettes 66-89, 66-90, 66-93], undated (Box 1, Item 66- 11)
  - Van Clute, Wilton; Nick (Mike) Pappas; and Kenneth R. Shaker. [audiocassettes 66-94, 66-95, 66-96, 66-97] (CD reference copy available), undated (Box 1, Item 66- 12)
  - [Colow, Maury?]; and Moe Fishman [audiocassette 66-75] (CD reference copy available), undated (Box 1, Item 66- 13)
  - Colow, Maury; Milton Wolff. [audiocassettes 66-98, 66-99] (CD reference copy available), undated (Box 1, Item 66- 14)
  - Davidow, Ruth; George Foucek; Donald MacLeod; and Wilbur Ed Wellman. [audiocassettes 66-79, 66-101] (CD reference copy available), undated (Box 1, Item 66- 15)
  - Durem, Rebecca (Schulman). Landis: "It was my understanding that the State Department...threw a little difficulty in your way before the first group [of nurses] got its passports..." [audiocassettes 66-146, 66-147] (CD reference copy available), undated (Box 1, Item 66- 16)
  - Eider, Louis. [audiocassettes 66-102, 66-103] (CD reference copy available), undated (Box 1, Item 66- 17)
  - Fishman, Moe; and Harold Smith. "Bryce Coleman, whose body I saw outside of Villanueva de Canada..." [audiocassette 66-151] (CD reference copy available), Jun 1, 1964 (Box 1, Item 66- 18)
  - Fisher, Harry; Steve Nelson; Charles Nusser; and Harold Smith. On Brunete. [audiocassettes 66-123, 66-131, 66-141] (CD reference copy available), Apr 1964 (Box 1, Item 66- 19)
  - Foucek, George; Sara Houlihan; Ruth Keller; Donald MacLeod; Donald Thayer; Wilbur Ed Wellman. After the Belchite Action. [audiocassette 66-108] (CD reference copy available), undated (Box 1, Item 66- 20)
  - Foucek, George; Sidney Levine; Donald MacLeod; and Steve Nelson. Added Material on the Ebro; Terrain at the Battle of Aragon. [audiocassettes 66-104, 66-109] (CD reference copy available), undated (Box 1, Item 66- 21)
  - Foucek, George; Sidney Levine; Donald MacLeod; and Donald Thayer. Teruel. [audiocassettes 66-105, 66-106, 66-107] (CD reference copy available), undated (Box 1, Item 66- 22)
  - Goddard, Howard Owen; Evelyn Hutchins; and Gabriel Jack Quinones [audiocassettes 66-81, 66-112, 66-113], undated (Box 1, Item 66- 23)
  - Goddard, Howard Owen; Evelyn Hutchins; and Gabriel Jack Quinones [audiocassettes 66-112, 66-114] [Reel-to-reel tape is inaudible; try cassettes], undated (Box 1, Item 66- 24)
  - Goff, Irving; and Harold Smith. "Johnson was in command of the base, DeWitt Parker was commissar..." [audiocassettes 66-115, 66-116] (CD reference copy available), undated (Box 1, Item 66- 25)
  - Gittelson, Lester; Herman Klein; Max Robert Klonsky. Gittelson: "I was with the original GW Battalion, but... in July 1937, we became part of the ALB because... most of the men in the GWB and the ALB were either killed or wounded. I recall the day of the first major offensive vividly..." [audiocassettes 66-120, 66-126] [Not transferable], undated (Box 1, Item 66- 26)
  - Goff, Irving; Benjamin Goldstein. On Fuentes. [audiocassettes 66-117, 66-118] [Not transferable], undated (Box 1, Item 66- 27)
  - Groden, Daniel Samuel [audiocassettes 66-119, 66-120] (CD reference copy available), undated (Box 1, Item 66- 28)
  - Harriman, Manny; and Allan Donald McNeil. "I had in my possession ...[documents that] were seized by the Eastern [?] Committee while I was in Pittsburgh during the infamous Jewish Cultural Center situation..." [audiocassette 82], undated (Box 1, Item 66- 29)
  - Harriman, Manny; William Gilmore Wheeler. Harriman on MacKenzie-Papineau Battalion at Ebro; Wheeler on Jarama. [Not transferable] [audiocassettes 66-159, 66-160], undated (Box 1, Item 66- 30)
  - Kaufman, Rubin. [audiocassette 66-96] (CD reference copy available), undated (Box 1, Item 66- 31)
  - Keller, Fred Paul. [audiocassettes 66-121, 66-122, 66-123] (CD reference copy available), undated (Box 1, Item 66- 32)
  - Keller, Fred Paul; Abraham Osheroff. [audiocassettes 66-103, 66-107, 66-124] (CD reference copy available), undated (Box 1, Item 66- 33)
  - Klein, Herman. On first week in September, 1938, in the Sierra Caballs: "I was in the Third Company of the Lincoln-Washington under the command of Bill Wheeler..." [audiocassettes 66-125, 66-129], Dec 1965 (Box 1, Item 66- 34)
  - Klein, Herman; and Steve Nelson. [audiocassettes 66-83, 66-137, 66-138] [Not transferable], undated (Box 1, Item 66- 35)
  - Klein, Herman; Charles Nusser; and Max Robert Klonsky. On Brunete; "...Martin Hourihan wounded in the April 5th attack? He was."; comments on the draft of Landis' book. [audiocassette 66-128] (CD reference copy available), Apr 3, 1965 (Box 1, Item 66- 36)
  - Klein, Herman; Charles Nusser; Max Robert Klonsky; and Harold Smilth. Smith, commander of battalion headquarters company on the staff structure and events surrounding the loss of Lardner; Nusser or Klonsky on issues concerning the publication of Landis's book. [audiocassette 66-127] (CD reference copy available), undated (Box 1, Item 66- 37)
  - Landis, Arthur; and Isadore Tivin. Landis demonstration tape, with instructions for veterans on how to make tapes; experience with MacKenzie-Papineau Battalion; Tivin on arrival at Albacete and training camp in Madrigueras. [audiocassettes 66-156, 66-157] (CD reference copy available), undated (Box 1, Item 66- 38)
  - Levine, Sidney; Donald MacLeod; Donald Thayer; and Wilbur Ed Wellman. Landis: "This tape is an excellent introduction"; MacLeod with transport, and covers a much wider field; Thayer on fighting in both towns as a lieutenant; Wellman on fighting with Lincolns at Quinto and taking of Hill 666; taking of Belchite. [audiocassettes 66-133, 66-134] (CD reference copy available), undated (Box 1, Item 66- 39)
  - Levine, Sidney; Donald Thayer. Primarily on Brunete Front. (CD reference copy available), undated (Box 1, Item 66- 40)
  - Love, Vaughn Costine; Steve Nelson; and Louis Secundy. Love on reasons why, as a black man, he volunteered for the SCW. [audiocassettes 66-143, 66-158] (CD reference copy available), Apr 3, 1965 (Box 2, Item 66- 41)
  - MacLeod, Donald Transport unit called the 2nd Regiment de Tren on Brunete. [audiocassettes 66-131, 66-132] (CD reference copy available), undated (Box 2, Item 66- 42)
  - Munday, Arthur; and Charles Nusser. [audiocassette 66-136] (CD reference copy available), Mar 7, 1965 (Box 2, Item 66- 43)
  - Nelson, Steve. Nelson: "When the Madrid campaign was over, all the men... wanted to get back to Paris..." [audiocassettes 66-97, 66-142] (CD reference copy available), Jul 4, 1964 (Box 2, Item 66- 44)
  - Nelson, Steve; and Charles Nusser. Nelson's response to criticisms of Landis about quality of earlier tapes: "I have perhaps as much information as any single American who was in the Brunete campaign... " [audiocassette 66-139] (CD reference copy available), undated (Box 2, Item 66- 45)
  - Nelson, Steve; Charles Nusser; and Harold Smith. [audiocassette 66-104] (CD reference copy available), Apr 1964 (Box 2, Item 66- 46)
  - Nelson, Steve; and Al Warren. Nelson: "I arrived in Albacete somewhere around the middle of April in 1937. We came in from France by a little fishing boat... ran into an Italian destroyer on the way..." [audiocassettes 66-93, 66-158] (CD reference copy available), undated (Box 2, Item 66- 47)
  - Parker, Max. From the First Transport Regiment, Prisoner [audiocassettes 66-144, 66-145] (CD reference copy available), undated (Box 2, Item 66- 48)
  - Sennett, William [and Songs?]. [audiocassettes 66-142, 66-148, 66-149] (CD reference copy available), undated (Box 2, Item 66- 49)
  - Smith, Harold. Equipment of Washington Battalion when they went into Brunete... [audiocassette 66-150] (CD reference copy available), undated (Box 2, Item 66- 50)
  - Stuart, Yale. [audiocassettes 66-132, 66-152, 66-153] (CD reference copy available), undated (Box 2, Item 66- 51)
  - Taft, Anne (I). Side 2: "One day...a truck drove up and Dr. Bethune arrived with a refrigerator and blood for transfusions, and set up the transfusion service for us..." [audiocassette 66-155] [Not transferable], undated (Box 2, Item 66- 52)
  - Taft, Anne (II). [audiocassette 66-154] (CD reference copy available), undated (Box 2, Item 66- 53)
  - Thayer, Donald. Current Medical Problems. [audiocassette 66-126] (CD reference copy available), undated (Box 2, Item 66- 54)
  - Unknown Interviewee. Jarama. [audiocassette 66-128] (CD reference copy available), undated (Box 2, Item 66- 55)
  - Zlotnick, Louis. From Chicago to New York to France, and Over the Mountain to Spain... [audiocassettes 66-129, 66-143], undated (Box 2, Item 66- 56)
- Series II: Miscellaneous Reel-to-Reel Audiotapes, 1945-1970.
  - Unrelated to Landis Book Project: Moe Fishman, Steve Nelson, and Charles Nusser Discussion of African-Americans in VALB, [1967?] (Box 2, Item 66-57)
  - Unrelated to Landis Book Project: Moe Fishman --Discussing the registration of VALB as Communist Front Organization. [Damaged], undated (Box 2, Item 66- 58)
  - Unrelated to Landis Book Project: [Fritz Kreisler Music?] [audiocassettes 66-121, 66-122, 66-123], [Nov. 20, 1957?] (Box 2, Item 66- 59)
  - Unrelated to Landis Book Project: Landis: [History of the Spanish Civil War?] [audiocassettes 66-133?, 66-134?], undated (Box 2, Item 66- 60)
  - Unrelated to Landis Book Project: Landis: Reply to Moe Fishman, [1974?] (Box 2, Item 66- 61)
  - Unrelated to Landis Book Project: Landis: VALB Book, undated (Box 2, Item 66- 62)
  - Unrelated to Landis Book Project: Musicians Congress [audiocassettes 66-105, 66-106, 66-107], [June 15, 1965?] (Box 2, Item 66- 63)
  - Unrelated to Landis Book Project: Song Fest [Jane Collendar's House?], 1945 (Box 2, Item 66- 64)
  - Unrelated to Landis Book Project: Bart Van der Schelling (CD reference copy available), Sep 23, 1969 (Box 2, Item 66- 65)
  - Unrelated to Landis Book Project: Bart Van der Schelling (CD reference copy available), [June 1969?] (Box 2, Item 66- 66)
  - Unrelated to Landis Book Project: Bart Van der Schelling (I) (CD reference copy available), Feb 1970 (Box 2, Item 66- 67)
  - Unrelated to Landis Book Project: Bart Van der Schelling (II) (CD reference copy available), Feb 1970 (Box 2, Item 66- 68)
  - Unrelated to Landis Book Project: Bart Van der Schelling: Singing (CD reference copy available), Oct 1964 (Box 2, Item 66- 69)
  - Unrelated to Landis Book Project: Bart Van der Schelling: Singing (CD reference copy available), undated (Box 2, Item 66- 70)
  - Unrelated to Landis Book Project: Bart Van der Schelling and Others: Singing (CD reference copy available), Oct 13, 1968 (Box 2, Item 66- 71)
- Unprocessed Materials (Box 3, Box 4, Box 5)